<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>$> cat /var/log/e770r</title><link>https://log.jubril.me/</link><description>Recent content on $> cat /var/log/e770r</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2021 s1ntaxe770r</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 02:37:19 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://log.jubril.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>TLS in a Nutshell</title><link>https://log.jubril.me/posts/tls-in-a-nutshell/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 02:37:19 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://log.jubril.me/posts/tls-in-a-nutshell/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="tls-in-a-nutshell">TLS in a nutshell&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>So it&amp;rsquo;s 1 am once again and I suddenly find myself questioning how the web works from the ground up(not even kidding this time), after roughly 30mins of re validating my knowledge, i have arrived at TLS whilst watching a nice talk by Daniel Stenberg, the author of curl,talk is over &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pUxyukqoXR4"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here&lt;/a>
btw
. In this talk Daniel goes over how the web has evolved from HTTP/1.1 down to HTTP2
and now HTTP 3 which is apparently going to save us all(no offense,i think &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QUIC"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">QUIC&lt;/a>
) is an amazing protocol, but that&amp;rsquo;s besides the point here.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="so-what-is-my-point-here">So what is my point here?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>well every so often I ask myself if I where to explain &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> to someone would i really be able to do it? if the answer is no , then it&amp;rsquo;s safe to say I don&amp;rsquo;t know enough about said topic, which means I need to do more research or find a way to put words together so the other person can understand. And this was the case with TLS,
whilst watching Daniel&amp;rsquo;s presentation I honestly never thought about explaining TLS, I mean i&amp;rsquo;ve tried once, but i&amp;rsquo;m quite sure the other person understood only because he was a technical person and not because i did a good job. So now i attempt to explain TLS in as few words as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://i.gifer.com/PlA0.gif"
alt="quic"/>
lol get it? quic. Okay enough with the bad jokes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So you know that little lock icon 🔒 you see in your browser when you head to your favorite website? TLS has something to do with that. Essentially TLS ensures that whoever you want to talk to on the inter webs is who they say they are, This means if i&amp;rsquo;m going to hipstergram.com, TLS ensures that i am indeed browsing hipstergram.com and what ever I am talking to hipstergram about stays between us, this could be something like login details , password details which would traditionally be visible to someone who is on the same wifi network as me, this is why you get that warning from your browser when you are browsing websites using HTTP, AKA websites without a lock icon. And now you maybe wondering&amp;hellip; How?
&lt;img src="https://media3.giphy.com/media/l4FGnHKwXZpdYu208/giphy.gif?cid=3640f6095bcf96f74f3847334945c030"
alt="how"/>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To do this TLS uses a combination of symmetric and asymmetric encryption to secure the communication between you and hipstergram, in the case of symmetric encryption me and hipstergram both agree to encrypt our messages using a shared key that has been predetermined ahead of time and this is how we both communicate, but this has one obvious downside if a bad guy somehow finds this key, he can now see all the pictures of my cat i&amp;rsquo;m uploading and possibly my login information if i&amp;rsquo;m signing in at that time. So to solve this problem the first time you visit a webpage your browser verify the webpage using something called the SSL or TLS handshake(you might hear both being used, the main point being TLS is the newer version of SSL) , which is basically a short conversation between your browser and the website to be sure he is who he says he is, it goes a little something like this :&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Browser: hey, we need to talk but i&amp;rsquo;ll only speak to you over a secure channel&lt;/p>
&lt;p>hipstergram.com: sure, i&amp;rsquo;ll send you my TLS certificate along with my public key&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Browser: sure,let me verify that by asking the person who gave you this(certificate authority).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Browser: Okay looks good, here&amp;rsquo;s a symmetric encryption key(also called a session key) which you can use to decipher all the messages i send to you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>hipstergram.com: sure!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And now you can safely login and like picture of your favorite cat, without prying eyes.
This took me way longer than it should have, because apparently explaining TLS is hard, there&amp;rsquo;s usually too much detail that it becomes overwhelming on or too little that it&amp;rsquo;s unsatisfactory, so i hope i did a decent job of striking a balance and hopefully you now know a lot more about transport layer security than when you came.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="a-bit-more-technical-but-great-reads">A bit more technical but great reads&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>🤩 The original TLS specification: &lt;a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2246#ref-XDR"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2246#ref-XDR&lt;/a>
Obligatory Wikipedia reference: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security&lt;/a>
Little more on TLS handshakes: &lt;a href="https://www.digicert.com/how-tls-ssl-certificates-work"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.digicert.com/how-tls-ssl-certificates-work&lt;/a>
&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Infrastructure Automation With Kubestack</title><link>https://log.jubril.me/posts/infra-automation-with-kubestack/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 19:15:43 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://log.jubril.me/posts/infra-automation-with-kubestack/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="infrastructure-automation-with-kubestack">Infrastructure Automation with Kubestack&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Over the weekend I got to try out &lt;a href="https://kubestack.com"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kubestack&lt;/a>
and in this post, I would be giving some of my thoughts on it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>FULL DISCLAIMER: while I am being paid to write this post the opinions and views expressed here are completely mines.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="so-whats-this-thing-anyway">So what&amp;rsquo;s this thing anyway?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>That was my first question as I have only ever heard about Kubestack in passing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kubestack is a &lt;a href="https://about.gitlab.com/topics/gitops/"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitOps&lt;/a>
framework aimed at simplifying the process of spinning up a Kubernetes cluster and automating subsequent deployments to your cluster. At the time of writing, Kubestack supports GKE, AKS, and EKS. Alright, now I know what it is but how is this any different than building my own CI/CD pipeline? Only one way to find out&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="getting-started">Getting started&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Before this, I have only made one attempt at automating how I deploy Kubernetes on azure, so if this worked out it would be such a joy because my last experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t go too well. So for the majority of this process, I would keep comparing my experience to my last attempt at something like this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enough talk let&amp;rsquo;s get right to it. The quickest way of getting started with Kubestack is by going through the &lt;a href="https://www.kubestack.com/framework/documentation/tutorial-get-started"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">getting started&lt;/a>
guide. The guide is split into three parts which I find very nice as it allowed me to digest an individual section before moving to the next.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="kubestack-command-line">Kubestack command line&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The setup here was quite straightforward, grab the binary, unzip and move it to your path, before I proceeded with the rest of the tutorial I decided to explore a bit by viewing some of the subcommand available. Honestly, I have no real complaints here, the subcommands are clearly explained and flags are consistent. Although I would like to see tab completion, that&amp;rsquo;s just personal preference 😄&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="bootstrapping-your-cluster">Bootstrapping your cluster&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Creating a cluster with Kubestack gets even easier as it automatically generates the base terraform&lt;/p>
&lt;p>code. This is powerful because one you can now generate the configuration for all supported clouds and two I no longer have to copy and paste most of my code from a previous project. Once you have your &amp;ldquo;repository&amp;rdquo; initialized you only have to change three values to get going.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Where things started to get tricky for me was the inheritance model the terraform code Kubestack generated uses, But this might be due to my lack of experience in that area but it&amp;rsquo;s something to look out for.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="testing-locally">Testing locally&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Kubestack has a neat feature that will provision a local Kubernetes cluster using &lt;a href="https://kind.sigs.k8s.io/"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">KinD&lt;/a>
and test your configuration against it, the advantage of this can&amp;rsquo;t be emphasized enough, I&amp;rsquo;ve broken a good chunk of my infrastructure simply because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a sandbox environment to test against.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, Kubestack generates a docker image with a few tools installed e.g(Kustomize, Terraform)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I found this quite convenient as I had an older version of terraform installed so I just opted to use the docker image instead. Creating a service principal for my account was a fairly smooth experience, the only real problem I ran into was giving to my service account. I ran into the following &lt;a href="https://login.microsoftonline.com/error?code=50076"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">error&lt;/a>
which I was able to resolve by granting the account permission through the Azure portal.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="deploying">Deploying&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This was equally as easy creating two workspaces and deploying resources in each was pretty straightforward, one new concept (for me at least) is Kubestack would set up DNS per environment so this interesting to see.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="automation">Automation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This was the part I was looking forward to the most. The goal is simple. Have a GitHub action setup in such a way that I can deploy to different environments and the pipeline would apply the Configuration.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="did-it-work">Did it work?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Yes! Of all the steps this took me the least amount of time to complete, the only problem I ran into was base64 encoding my credentials which I got around by removing &lt;code>-w&lt;/code> because line breaks are automatically ignored on Mac, even at that it took me about 10mins to set up the entire pipeline.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While I&amp;rsquo;m a huge fan of Github actions it would be nice to have the option of seeing the setup for other CI services like GitLab&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="beyond-the-tutorial">Beyond the tutorial&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>And now for the fun part, trying things outside the tutorial. For this part, I wanted to see what else I could deploy to my cluster so I consulted the &lt;a href="https://www.kubestack.com/catalog"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">catalog&lt;/a>
section and picked Argo CD ( other resources such as Flux Prometheus Operator and Cert Manger are also available ), as I mentioned earlier I&amp;rsquo;m very new to the inheritance model Kubestack uses and so this did not end too well, but this was not a total failure I saw this as an opportunity to really stretch the Pipeline I had just built out and so I made one more failing deployment and then I was able to rollback by simply reverting my commit, this is where GitOps truly shines, the fact that your infrastructure can now be thought of as commits in Git, Although I think the documentation could do a better job towards guiding people new to this style of configuration.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="additional-concerns">Additional concerns&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As I worked my way through the tutorial one thing that bothered me were the deprecation warnings that popped up every now and then, as i mentioned earlier this is something that could be fixed in a subsequent release.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At the end of the entire process I had but one question.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Was it worth it? Yes, it was. this is hands down the quickest I&amp;rsquo;ve ever set up something like this the entire process took me about an hour, compared to my previous attempt which took me three days :). So this is a huge saving in effort and time, a few additional things i&amp;rsquo;d like to see are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>more resources in the catalouge section.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>more clouds supported.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>That sums up my experience with Kubestack feel free to check it out over &lt;a href="https://kubestack.com"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here&lt;/a>
and the complete code from the tutorial over &lt;a href="https://github.com/s1ntaxe770r/kubestack-sandbox"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here&lt;/a>
&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>What the heck is a data plane?</title><link>https://log.jubril.me/posts/data-plane/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 12:49:07 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://log.jubril.me/posts/data-plane/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.treehugger.com/thmb/zHEqqllMa66MSzzitQ8G5pp136Y=/768x0/filters:no_upscale%28%29:max_bytes%28150000%29:strip_icc%28%29/__opt__aboutcom__coeus__resources__content_migration__mnn__images__2014__09__shutterstock_556793080-b4a5fd4b2287434b959ef955e39a7aa7.jpg"
alt="Paper Airplane Sets Record With 82-Mile Flight"/>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As i sit here at 12:50am . I attempt to answer the question that&amp;rsquo;s been on my mind for days now. &amp;ldquo;What the heck is a data plane?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To fully understand we need to back track a bit. A data plane is one of two major components of a &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/topics/microservices/what-is-a-service-mesh"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">service mesh&lt;/a>
, yet that alone is far from the answer i seek.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="taking-a-closer-look">Taking a closer look&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To find the answers i seek, it&amp;rsquo;s worth taking look at the architecture of a typical service mesh and analyze from there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;span class="image-container">&lt;span class="link">&lt;img class="img" src="https://istio.io/latest/docs/ops/deployment/architecture/arch.svg"
alt="istio architecture"/>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="caption">&lt;span class="title">istio service mesh architecture&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When a request comes into service A on lets &lt;code>/login&lt;/code> the data plane ( AKA the sidecar proxy, in this case the envoy instance in the diagram ) is responsible for resolving what service the request is to be forwarded to, collect metrics , perform healthchecks and a bunch of other stuff the service mesh user might have configred it to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tldr">TL;DR&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A data plane is a component of a service mesh responsible for:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Routing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Load Balancing&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Health Checks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Observability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Service Discovery&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Popular examples inclued , &lt;a href="https://envoyproxy.io"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Envoy proxy&lt;/a>
, &lt;a href="https://nginx.com"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nginx&lt;/a>
, &lt;a href="https://traefik.io/"target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Traefik&lt;/a>
.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>First Post</title><link>https://log.jubril.me/posts/first-post/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 15:38:07 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://log.jubril.me/posts/first-post/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="wow-it-works">Wow it works&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Hello world&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>